{
  "q1": [
    {
      "question": "This man, who shared leadership with Crixus and Oenomaus, routed Mummius when he attacked against orders. Gaius Claudius Glaber tried to starve this man’s forces while they camped on the slopes of Mount Vesuvius. Many of this man’s supporters were crucified by Crassus along the Appian Way after they lost the Third Servile War. For ten points, name this former gladiator who died in 71 BC while leading a slave revolt against the Roman Republic.",
      "answer": "Spartacus"
    },
    {
      "question": "An artist from this country was influenced by Marcel Duchamp to weld together 42 bicycle frames. That artist, who filmed the aftermath of a 2008 earthquake in this country, also exhibited one million handmade porcelain sunflower seeds in England’s Tate Modern gallery. For ten points, name this country where artist and political activist Ai Weiwei consulted on the design of a “bird’s nest” stadium built for this country’s 2008 Summer Olympics.",
      "answer": "People’s Republic of China or Zhongguo"
    },
    {
      "question": "This battle’s winning side was greatly aided when they learned that an attack at “A-F” would take place; that information came by breaking the JN25 code. Dauntless dive bombers were used to great effect in this battle, as one side sunk the Akagi, Kaga and two other ships while only losing the Yorktown. For ten points, name this battle fought a month after the Battle of Coral Sea, a carrier battle that became the “turning point” of World War II’s Pacific theater.",
      "answer": "Battle of Midway"
    },
    {
      "question": "This event directly led to the passage of the Sullivan-Hoey Law. The owners of the central location of this event, Max Blanck and Isaac Harris, were acquitted of manslaughter charges when the prosecution was unable to prove that they knew a series of doors were locked. The ILGWU union gained traction in the wake of this event, in which some immigrant workers jumped nine stories to their death. For ten points, name this 1911 fire in a New York City factory.",
      "answer": "Triangle Shirtwaist factory fire"
    },
    {
      "question": "This ruler signed the Treaty of Ryswick to end a lengthy war against a “Grand Alliance” that opposed him. Earlier, this ruler had used the death of Philip IV and a dowry owed to this man’s nation to start the War of the Devolution. This king ended toleration for Huguenots in the Edict of Fontainebleau, which revoked the Edict of Nantes. The death of Cardinal Mazarin began the 72-year-long reign of, for ten points, what absolutist “Sun King” of France?",
      "answer": "Louis XIV"
    },
    {
      "question": "This composer protested in support of Alfred Dreyfus by refusing to perform in Paris in 1899. He included an “Arietta” and a tribute to Niels Gade in a ten-book set of 66 short piano pieces, and a tympani roll opens his only Piano Concerto, in A minor. This composer of the Lyric Pieces also wrote incidental music for a Henrik Ibsen play that includes “Anitra’s Dance” and “Morning Mood.” For ten points, name this nationalist Norwegian composer who wrote Peer Gynt.",
      "answer": "Edvard Grieg"
    },
    {
      "question": "One side in this battle repeatedly moved unarmed merchant ships into port to invoke the Hague Convention’s Article 16 and prevent the enemy from leaving. After damaging the Ajax, Achilles, and Exeter, the losing side in this battle made the mistake of retreating to Montevideo. Hans Langsdorff decided to scuttle his ship, Graf Spee, rather than continue this battle. For ten points, name this first naval battle of World War II, named for its location in the river that forms the border between Argentina and Uruguay.",
      "answer": "Battle of the River Plate or Battle of the Rio de La Plata"
    },
    {
      "question": "This project began thanks to a revolution started by the killing of a Chinese civilian and his donkey. Philippe-Jean Bunau-Varilla orchestrated a controversial treaty, later undone by the Torrijos-Carter Treaties, granting the US control over this project. “Gunboat diplomacy” against Colombia sparked a Central American country’s independence and the building of, for ten points, what canal that, in 1914, connected the Atlantic and Pacific Oceans?",
      "answer": "Panama Canal"
    },
    {
      "question": "This battle, whose site is commemorated at Chalmette National Park, included an assault on the defenders’ artillery position led by William Thornton. The attackers in this battle had no ladders to scale a series of three earthworks and suffered the death of their commander, Edward Pakenham. This American victory was technically fought after the signing of the Treaty of Ghent had ended the War of 1812. For ten points, name this battle in which Andrew Jackson defended a Louisiana port city.",
      "answer": "Battle of New Orleans"
    },
    {
      "question": "This mentor of Phog Allen played center on the McGill University football team in the 1890s. Luther Gulick asked this man for advice on keeping members of the Springfield YMCA in shape; this man used a pair of peach baskets in his ensuing invented game. The University of Kansas’ only losing coach in one sport is, ironically, this man. The NBA Hall of Fame is named after, for ten points, what inventor of basketball?",
      "answer": "James Naismith"
    }
  ],
  "q2": [
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The “transforming principle” of this molecule was discovered in an experiment on mice by Frederick Griffith. Evidence for this molecule’s purpose was found in a 1952 experiment using sulfur, phosphorous, and bacteriophages. X-ray diffraction pictures taken by Rosalind Franklin helped earn Watson and Crick a Nobel Prize for determining the double helix structure of, for ten points, what molecule that carries genetic instructions?",
        "answer": "DNA or deoxyribonucleic acid BONUS:ThesetwoAmericanscientistsperformedtheaforementioned1952experimentthatdemonstrated how DNA, not proteins, contained genetic material. ANSWER: Alfred Hershey and Martha Chase 2 The death of a ruler of this empire at the hands of Tamerlane led to an interregnum ended at the Battle of C¸amurlu. An Albanian revolt against this empire was led by a former general named Skanderbeg, and this empire defeated a Christian coalition at the Battle of Varna in 1444. Ibrahim the Mad and Murad the Great were sultans of, for ten points, what empire that, under Mehmed II, conquered Constantinople from the Byzantines in 1453? ANSWER: Ottoman Empire"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Ottoman Interregnum began with the death of this Ottoman sultan, called “the Thunderbolt,” and ended with Mehmed I’s aforementioned victory at C¸amurlu.",
        "answer": [
          "Bayezid I or Bayezid the Thunderbolt",
          "Bayezid Yildirim"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Fannie Lou Hamer led an African-American delegation from this state to the 1964 Democratic National Convention. In this state, Chaney, Goodman, and Schwerner were killed during the Freedom Summer voter registration drive; those killings were described as this state “burning.” James Meredith was the first African-American student admitted to this state’s flagship university in Oxford. Three years later, Meredith was shot and wounded while marching to, for ten points, what state’s capital of Jackson?",
        "answer": "Mississippi"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This civil rights activist was killed outside his Jackson home in June 1963 by Byron de la Beckwith, as portrayed in the movie The Ghosts of Mississippi.",
        "answer": "Medgar Evers"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This work ends by criticizing the “false security of peace,” citing Acts chapter 14, verse 22 for the idea that “tribulations” provide passage into heaven. Earlier, this document attacks the “human doctrine” that souls can “[fly] out of purgatory” after the payment of an indulgence; that attack is its 27th point. For ten points, name this document that was posted in Wittenburg in 1517 by Martin Luther, outlining his criticism of the Catholic Church in nearly 100 statements.",
        "answer": "95 Theses or Disputation on the Power of Indulgences"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Though the Theses don’t mention him by name, Luther’s criticism was largely aimed at this German preacher for his sale of indulgences for future sins.",
        "answer": "Johann Tetzel"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "A king of this nation died at Fredriksten, forcing his men to endure the Carolean Death March to return home. The Pruth River Campaign was waged by Russia against the Ottomans to capture that king of this nation. Another king from this nation was known as the “Lion of the North” and led Protestant forces at the Battle of Breitenfield. The House of Vasa once ruled, for ten points, what country led by Charles XII and Gustavus Adolphus in the Great Northern War and Thirty Years’ War, respectively?",
        "answer": "Kingdom of Sweden"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The aforementioned Pruth River Campaign began after Charles XII’s forces were wiped out at this June 1709 battle in modern Ukraine.",
        "answer": "Battle of Poltava"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "In a play by this author, a man who gave away all of his money at a banquet finds a hoard of gold while living in a cave in the wilderness. This author wrote a play in which the images of an armored head, a bloody child, and a crowned child warn a king of Scotland that he cannot be harmed by a man “of woman born,” though the king is later killed by Macduff anyways. For ten points, name this author of the historically inspired tragedies Timon of Athens and Macbeth.",
        "answer": "William Shakespeare"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The title character of this Shakespeare tragedy is a chieftain of the Volsci who is persuaded by his mother Volumnia to make peace with Rome in the 5th century BC.",
        "answer": "Coriolanus"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This country tried to kickstart its economy under the “Fifty Years of Progress in Five” program of Juscelino Kubitschek. A European-inspired Estado Novo period in this country marked the end of “coffee with milk” politics. The petroleum company Petrobras was nationalized in, for ten points, what country whose 20th century modernization included Oscar Niemeyer’s designing of a new capital city to replace Rio de Janeiro?",
        "answer": "Federative Republic of Brazil"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This Brazilian president and dictator was overthrown in a 1945 coup but returned to power in 1951, at which point he nationalized Brazil’s oil industry.",
        "answer": "Getu´lio Vargas"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The day before this event, the “Stennis Compromise” was offered to, and rejected by, its target. This event ended when third-in-command Robert Bork, having been promised a seat on the Supreme Court, followed orders that William Ruckelshaus and Elliot Richardson refused to carry out. October 20, 1973 was the date of, for ten points, what sub-scandal in which Richard Nixon ordered the firing of the special prosecutor in charge of Watergate?",
        "answer": "Saturday Night Massacre"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This man was the special prosecutor fired in the Saturday Night Massacre. After his firing, he remarked “Whether we shall continue to be a Government of laws and not of men is now for Congress and ultimately the American people.”",
        "answer": "Archibald Cox"
      }
    }
  ],
  "q3": [
    {
      "category": "The Warren Court",
      "prompt": "During the Supreme Court tenure of Earl Warren, name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "President who nominated Warren to the Supreme Court in 1953.",
          "answer": "Dwight D. Eisenhower"
        },
        {
          "question": "Set of first ten amendments to the Constitution that Warren actively incorporated against the states.",
          "answer": "Bill of Rights"
        },
        {
          "question": "Amendment cited in Trop v. Dulles, which ruled that loss of citizenship is cruel and unusual punishment.",
          "answer": "8th Amendment to the US Constitution"
        },
        {
          "question": "Set of rights, including the right to remain silent, given by police to suspects in custody after a 1966 case.",
          "answer": [
            "Miranda rights",
            "Miranda warning, etc.",
            "Miranda v. Arizona"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Political divisions that must be redrawn once every ten years, per Baker v. Carr. They can be gerrymandered.",
          "answer": "electoral districts or Congressional districts, etc."
        },
        {
          "question": "Newspaper whose case against L.B. Sullivan established the “actual malice” standard for libel.",
          "answer": "The New York Times"
        },
        {
          "question": "State sued by Clarence Brandenburg in a 1969 case about violent speech.",
          "answer": "Brandenburg v. Ohio"
        },
        {
          "question": "Associate justice who “defined” obscenity by saying “I know it when I see it” in 1964.",
          "answer": "Potter Stewart"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Scotland",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Tartan-patterned garments, similar to skirts, that originated in the Scottish Highlands.",
          "answer": "kilts"
        },
        {
          "question": "Musical instrument long considered a tool of war in the Scottish army, consisting of a chanter, drones, and a blowstick.",
          "answer": "bagpipes"
        },
        {
          "question": "London church where Edward Longshanks brought the captured Stone of Scone in 1296.",
          "answer": "Westminster Abbey"
        },
        {
          "question": "Knight who joined Andrew Moray to beat the English at Stirling Bridge, eight years before he was hanged for treason.",
          "answer": "William Wallace"
        },
        {
          "question": "1995 quasi-historical film in which Mel Gibson plays that knight.",
          "answer": "Braveheart"
        },
        {
          "question": "14th century King of Scots who beat Edward II at Bannnockburn in 1314.",
          "answer": "Robert the Bruce or Robert I"
        },
        {
          "question": "Rebellions in 1715 and 1745 that sought to restore a Catholic monarch to the British throne.",
          "answer": "Jacobite rebellions or Jacobite risings, etc."
        },
        {
          "question": "Last pitched battle on British soil, a 1746 battle that ended the rebellions in the previous question.",
          "answer": "Battle of Culloden Moor"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Tokugawa Shogunate",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Country ruled by the Tokugawa Shogunate.",
          "answer": [
            "Japan or Nippon",
            "Nihon"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Type of infrastructure built throughout the country to allow the “alternate attendance” policy to function, including the “Five Routes.”",
          "answer": [
            "roads",
            "Kaido"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Capital city of the Tokugawa shoguns.",
          "answer": "Edo or Tokyo"
        },
        {
          "question": "City that was the residence of the Emperor during the Tokugawa Era.",
          "answer": "Kyoto"
        },
        {
          "question": "Religious group persecuted by the shogunate after it was spread by European missionaries.",
          "answer": [
            "Christians or kirishitan",
            "Roman Catholics"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "City where, in 1615, Tokugawa forces captured a landmark castle and crushed the Toyotomi clan.",
          "answer": [
            "Osaka",
            "Osaka Castle"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Series of isolationist laws that closed the country from foreign contact during the Tokugawa era.",
          "answer": "sakoku"
        },
        {
          "question": "Battle in 1600 that marked the beginning of the shogunate, where Ieyasu defeated Ishida Mitsunari’s Western Army.",
          "answer": "Battle of Sekigahara"
        }
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q4": [
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) A charter in this modern-day state was given to Ferdinando Gorges, who never actually visited the New World, and John Mason. The first ship built by England in the New World was named for Sagadahoc, a colony in this state on the (20 pts)",
        "Kennebec River. Mistakes in the 1789 Treaty of Paris led to the Aroostook War in what is now this state. In 1820, after the (10 pts)",
        "Missouri Compromise, this state was created by splitting off from Massachusetts. For ten points, name this northeastern state whose capital moved in 1832 from Portland to Augusta."
      ],
      "answer": "Maine"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) A year after this revolt was put down, the Treaty of Middle Plantation was signed, recognizing land rights of local Native American tribes that remained obedient to the English. Landless freemen were granted voting rights by laws passed during this revolt by a reconstituted House of (20 pts)",
        "Burgesses. William Drummond and other participants in this revolt were hanged by Governor William (10 pts)",
        "Berkeley shortly after its namesake leader died of dysentery. Concern over Native American attacks triggered, for ten points, what 1676 revolt in which Jamestown was burned?"
      ],
      "answer": "Nathaniel Bacon’s Rebellion"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Ancient culture on this island included the worship of a woman holding two serpents in her hands, “the snake goddess,” and its art used the Horns of Consecration motif in honor of a sacred bull. In the second millennium BC, the (20 pts)",
        "Thera eruption on Santorini devastated this island to the south; that event and a possible Mycenaean invasion from the mainland may have ended a civilization centered on this island that used the still-undeciphered (10 pts)",
        "Linear A script and had its capital at Knossos. For ten points, name this largest Greek island, the home of the Minoan civilization."
      ],
      "answer": "Crete"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) A book about this concept in a Free Society was written by one of its critics, Paul Feyerabend. This concept’s “revolutionary” and “normal” phases were detailed in a 1962 book about the Structure of its (20 pts)",
        "Revolutions. Thomas Kuhn’s work on this subject introduced the term “paradigm shift” for momentous occasions in its history, such as (10 pts)",
        "Einstein’s theories of general relativity. For ten points, name this modern field of study divided into subfields such as biology, chemistry, and physics. ANSWER:science(acceptScienceinaFreeSociety;acceptTheStructure of Scientific Revolutions) (5) As Prime Minister, this man allowed journalists to be arrested for covering the “Ergenekon” trials. The Justice and Development Party was founded by this man, whose government was the target of a brief uprising by the (+) Peace at Home Council that they blamed on the Gu¨len movement, named for a Pennsylvania-based businessman named Fethullah Gu¨len. A July 2016 (*) coup d’etat in the streets of Ankara and Istanbul failed to oust, for ten points, what President of Turkey?"
      ],
      "answer": "Recep Tayyip Erdogan , but be lenient"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) William Momyer came under fire for suggesting that this group engage only in coastal duties. Members of this group trained at Moton Field. A subgroup of these people gained a famous nickname after painting the (20 pts)",
        "tails of their P-47s red. A member of this group, Chief Anderson, took Eleanor Roosevelt on a test flight that helped speed up the (10 pts)",
        "desegregation of the military. An Alabama university names, for ten points, what group of African American World War II pilots?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Tuskegee Airmen",
        "477th Bombardment Group",
        "332nd Fighter Group"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) During this man’s attempts at unification, he allied with the Soviet Union after signing a manifesto with Adolph Joffe. To gain the support of the Beiyang Army, this man promised the presidency to Yuan (20 pts)",
        "Shikai while orchestrating the Xinhai [shin-hai] Revolution against emperor Pu Yi. This man believed in nationalism, democracy, and livelihood - the (10 pts)",
        "“three principles of the people” - and founded the Kuomintang. For ten points, name this first president of the Republic of China."
      ],
      "answer": "Sun Yat-sen"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In this war, the first African American to command an American military unit, Oliver Law, was killed at the Battle of Brunete. The Conference of Nyon condemned Italian submarine attacks in this war, which included Operation (20 pts)",
        "Ru¨gen. The term “fifth column” was coined by Emilio Mola during this war. In this war, the Abraham Lincoln Brigade fought alongside republicans and the (10 pts)",
        "German Condor Legion bombed Guernica. For ten points, name this 1936 to 1939 war that ended when Francisco Franco captured Madrid."
      ],
      "answer": "Spanish Civil War"
    }
  ]
}